{"tossups": [{"question": "Isambard Kingdom Brunel designed the prefabricated Renkioi Hospital for use during this war. This war led to innovations in fashion named for Lords Raglan and Cardigan, as well as the Balaklava hood. During this war, the British Light Brigade attempted a suicidal charge commemorated in Tennyson\u2019s poem. For the point, name this war in which Russia fought a coalition of French, English, and Ottomans over a namesake peninsula.", "answer": "<b><u>Crimean</u></b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In his later years, this man adopted a strange triangular signature and wrote <em>The Book of</em> <em>Prophecies</em>, predicting a world emperor and a new crusade. Although he was awarded the title \u201cAdmiral of the Ocean Sea,\u201d this man was imprisoned during his third voyage for corruptly governing Hispaniola. According to legend, this Genoan\u2019s first voyage was funded when Queen Isabella I pawned her jewels. For the point, name this explorer who sailed for the new world in 1492.", "answer": "Christopher <b><u>Columbus</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man, who was known as \"Detroit Red\" during his street days, was shot at the Audubon Ballroom which left Betty Shabazz a widow. He was disciplined for claiming that John F. Kennedy's assassination was \"chickens coming home to roost\" before his trip to Mecca, which led him to seek racial reconciliation. For the point, name this disciple of Elijah Muhammad who was the militant spokesman for the Nation of Islam.", "answer": "<b><u>Malcolm X</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "After the Civil Liberties Act of 1988 was passed, people subject to this policy received letters of apology from the President and a check for twenty thousand dollars. This policy was set out in Executive Order 9066. This policy, upheld in the <em>Korematsu</em> case, targeted George Takei's family and other Nisei, who were confined to places such as Manzanar. For the point, name this World War II policy which removed an immigrant group from the West Coast to camps.", "answer": "<b><u>Japanese internment</u></b> [or equivalents]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This state was represented in the Senate by a man who led the Anti-Mafia Committee and conducted hearings which led to the establishment of the Comics Code Authority. This home state of Estes Kefauver was also represented by actor Fred Thompson and by Al Gore Sr. and Jr. This state lends its name to a river that was extensively developed during the New Deal. For the point, identify this namesake of a \"Valley Authority\" and the site of the Battle of Shiloh near Memphis.", "answer": "<b><u>Tennessee</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This king condemned adoptionism at the Council of Frankfurt and established the <em>missi dominici</em> system. A minuscule script was developed under the direction of Alcuin (<b>AL-koo-in</b>) of York in this king's capital at Aachen. At Roncevaux (<b>ron-suh-voh</b>) Pass, this man's rearguard under Roland was massacred by Basques. This grandson of Charles Martel was given a new title by Pope Leo III on Christmas Day. For the point, name this ruler of the Franks in the 8th & 9th centuries.", "answer": "<b><u>Charlemagne</u></b> [or <b><u>Carolus Magnus</u></b>; <b><u>Charles the Great</u></b>; or <b><u>Charles I</u></b>; prompt on <b><u>Charles</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In a rumination on where the support base of Louis-Napoleon was, this man posited that \"history repeats itself, first as tragedy, then as farce.\" He outlined his disagreements with his home country's Socialist Party in the <em>Critique of the Gotha Program</em> and extended concepts such as the \"surplus value of labor\" in a magnum opus finished by his associate Friedrich Engels. For the point, name this primary author of \"The Communist Manifesto.\"", "answer": "Karl <b><u>Marx</u></b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "During the 1980s in this nation, the Islamic Ennhada movement was violently suppressed. This nation\u2019s longtime ruling Neo-Destour Party was headed by Habib Bourgiba. In one battle in this nation, forces led by Lloyd Fredendall were defeated by Erwin Rommel at Kasserine Pass. In this nation, a produce vendor in Sidi Bouzid set himself on fire in 2011, starting a revolution. For the point, name this nation ruled by Zine (<b>ZEEN</b>) El Abidine Ben Ali until the Arab Spring.", "answer": "<b><u>Tunisia</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Four months after this event, an airport was seized in its \"mini\" version. Gains made during this event allowed this event's organizers to commit the Hue (way) Massacre. American reaction to this event threw temporary support to Eugene McCarthy in the Democratic Presidential primaries, and caused a momentous on-air condemnation of military policy by Walter Cronkite. For the point, name this January 1968 attack on Saigon and other targets by the Viet Cong.", "answer": "<b><u>Tet</u> </b>Offensive", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The plant manufacturing these items offered \"an honest day's pay for an honest day's work,\" which amounted to a previously unheard-of five dollar per day wage. That was done so that the employees who built these items could afford one. These items were produced at a rate of one every ten seconds at River Rouge's assembly line. For the point, identify this car, an iconic early American automobile which succeeded the Model A and was produced by Henry Ford's company.", "answer": "Ford <b><u>Model T</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A man of this last name said \"if nominated I will not run, if elected I will not serve\" to quash a rumored Presidential campaign. That man's brother, also of this surname, sponsored a \"Silver Purchase Act\" as well as an 1890 bill aimed at monopolies, his Antitrust Act. This name of Senator John was held by a general who declared \"war is hell\" and delivered Savannah as a \"Christmas gift.\" For the point, give this last name of \"march to the sea\" general William Tecumseh.", "answer": "<b><u>Sherman</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This musical was based on Mary Main's book about a \"woman with a whip.\" A mistress in this musical sings the song \"Another Suitcase in Another Hall,\" shortly after the funeral of the title character is depicted in \"Oh What a Circus.\" Che Guevara narrates this musical, whose most famous song asserts \"The truth is I never left you\" and asks \"don't cry for me.\" For the point, name this Tim Rice and Andrew Lloyd Webber musical about a first lady of Argentina.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Evita</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {"question": "The government created by this document negotiated the Treaty of Fort Stanwix with the Iroquois. This document contained a provision for uniting with Canada and was supposed to be revised at the Annapolis Convention. This document authorized the Northwest Ordinance and did not provide enough military power to combat Shays' Rebellion. For the point, name this weak, pre-Constitution charter of the United States government.", "answer": "<b><u>Articles of Confederation</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A 1991 Barnard and Walt experiment used this technology to analyze human blood, and this technology is the basis of the medical \"bronchoscope.\" In 1977, this technology was first used in Suffolk, England to transmit telephone signals; by 1987, a line of this kind laid across the Atlantic could carry 37,000 calls at once. For the point, identify this light-based data transmission technology which underlies reliable high-speed Internet and television.", "answer": "<b><u>fiber optic</u></b>s [or <b><u>optical fiber</u></b>; prompt on partial answer; prompt on <b><u>FIOS</u></b> or other brand names]", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Misc Science"}, {"question": "This man once famously beat up Robin Ventura after Ventura charged the mound, an act that George W. Bush, who owned this man\u2019s team at the time, admired him for. Although he is the all-time leader in no-hitters with 7, he never threw a perfect game. He is also the only Major League Baseball player to have his number retired by 3 different teams: the Angels, Astros, and Rangers. For the point, name this Major League Baseball pitcher whose 5,714 career strikeouts rank first in baseball history.", "answer": "Nolan <b><u>Ryan</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This film was criticized for showing disorganized mob fighting rather than disciplined use of the schiltron, for presenting the use of spears against cavalry as a medieval innovation, and for changing the name of Murron. It also posits a historically absent tradition of face-painting and forgets to include the bridge in the Battle of Stirling Bridge. For the point, identify this 1995 film in which William Wallace, portrayed by Mel Gibson, fights the English.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Braveheart</u></b></em>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This person inspired Alfred Hitchcock\u2019s film <em>The Lodger</em>. He included a kidney in a letter he sent to George Lusk that opened with the line \u201cFrom hell.\u201d Some have speculated that he was the painter Walter Sickert or the doctor William Gull. This man, who was active in the Whitechapel district, caused the resignation of London\u2019s police commissioner. For the point, name this nineteenth-century serial killer of at least five prostitutes in London.", "answer": "<b><u>Jack the Ripper</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Conditions in this city during the 1760s were volatile due to its south side burning down in the \"Tavern Fire\" followed by a smallpox outbreak the next year. This city is where Andrew Oliver was attacked in 1765 and then burnt in effigy at the Liberty Tree. Thomas Hutchinson, who lived in this city as governor, was also attacked in this city, as were Crispus Attucks and other demonstrators. For the point, name this location of a 1770 \"massacre.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Boston</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man adopted the Monnet (<b>MOE-nay</b>) Plan for government-led economic growth. He assumed his country's presidency a second time on the condition a new constitution with a more powerful executive be drafted. As president, he signed the Evian Accords that ended the Algerian War of Independence. During World War II, this general led resistance troops that fought the Vichy regime. For the point, name this French president and leader of the Free French.", "answer": "Charles <b><u>de Gaulle</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Pairs of this general class of objects called <em>daisho</em> were often displayed on ornamental stands. An instructional text on using them, divided into sections called Earth, Fire, Water, Wind, & Void, is the <em>Book of Five Rings</em> by Miyamoto Musashi. The <em>jitte</em> was designed to break these objects, which were used in pairs that included the short <em>wakizashi</em>. For the point, name these weapons banned during the Meiji era to weaken the samurai, which include the curved katana.", "answer": "samurai <b><u>sword</u></b>s [or <em><b><u>tsurugi</u></b></em>; <em><b><u>ken</u></b></em>; <em><b><u>nihonto</u></b></em>; don\u2019t accept \"katana\"; prompt on <b><u>weapon</u></b>s]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man, who took a physics class from Christian Doppler in conjunction with his studies at the St. Thomas's Abbey of Brno, did experiments on bees which were destroyed after his death to save on a tax bill. He discovered laws of segregation and independent assortment during his more lasting work on the monastery's garden with pea plants. For the point, name this Austrian monk who discovered the basic laws of genetic inheritance.", "answer": "Gregor <b><u>Mendel</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In Haida myth, this character brings food to the first humans after finding them in a clamshell. This animal, like coyote, is a common American Indian trickster god; in other systems, these birds keep Odin informed of the news. This animal was selected to be the namesake of a sports team due to Edgar Allen Poe\u2019s association with Baltimore. For the point, name this culturally significant bird which is similar to the slightly smaller crow.", "answer": "<b><u>raven</u></b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Anthropology"}, {"question": "This city is the current home of the Babylonian Ishtar Gate and the Pergamon Altar, which both reside on its \"Museum Island.\" This city also contains a history museum called the \"Topography of Terror\" and an arch marking the start of a boulevard lined with linden trees. This city was where the Bundestag (<b>BOON-dess-tog</b>) moved in 1999, ending the capital functions of Bonn. For the point, name this home of the Brandenburg Gate which was once divided by a wall.", "answer": "<b><u>Berlin</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This event is commemorated by a large Doric column which is topped with a golden urn and which can be ascended through a 311 step spiral staircase. Many details of this event are relayed in the diary of Samuel Pepys. Robert Hooke worked as a surveyor in the aftermath of this event, which also led to the commissioning of many churches from Christopher Wren. For the point, name this 1666 disaster which necessitated the rebuilding of the capital of England.", "answer": "Great <b><u>Fire of London</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man borrows money from plantation owner Arthur Swille in Ishmael Reed's <em>Flight to</em> <em>Canada.</em> Raymond Massey repeatedly played this man on stage and screen, including in Robert Sherwood's play about his youth. He is described as the \"powerful western fallen star\" in \"When Lilacs Last in the Dooryard Bloom'd,\" and as \"fallen cold and dead\" in \"O Captain! My Captain!\" For the point, Walt Whitman twice eulogized what assassinated President?", "answer": "Abraham <b><u>Lincoln</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "Future Secretary of Defense Donald Rumsfeld was one of the Republicans who advocated for this bill in Congress. This law was challenged by Ollie's Barbecue in the <em>Katzenbach v. McClung</em> case, which was ruled in the same way as the more definitive <em>Heart of Atlanta Motel</em> decision. This law was filibustered by Robert Byrd but ultimately passed and was signed by Lyndon Johnson. For the point, name this 1964 law outlawing most racial discrimination.", "answer": "<b><u>Civil Rights Act</u></b> of 1964", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "While serving as Secretary of War, this man oversaw the building of the Washington Aqueduct and commissioned the Pacific Railroad Surveys which ultimately led to the decision to make the Gadsden Purchase. This man resigned as Senator from Mississippi on that state's secession, and four years later he wore his wife's clothing to try to escape. For the point, name this man who sat at Birmingham, Richmond, and Danville as the president of the Confederacy.", "answer": "Jefferson <b><u>Davis</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A novel promoting this political party explained that Baron Rothe was manipulating American currency and was written by the creator of its pamphlet <em>Coin's Financial School</em>. This party was dubbed \"gibbering idiots\" by the \"sage of Emporia,\" William White. This party, which issued the Omaha Platform, supported rail nationalization and free silver coinage. For the point, name this farmers' party which enjoyed brief success behind William Jennings Bryan.", "answer": "<b><u>Populist</u></b> Party [or <b><u>People's</u></b> Party; or the <b><u>Populists</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s military campaigns were chronicled by the historian Arrian. His life was once saved by Cleitus the Black in a battle at the Granicus River. He took Stateira as his second wife in a mass wedding he arranged at Susa, and he met his longtime companion Hephaestion while studying under Aristotle. After this man\u2019s death, his generals fought amongst themselves in the Wars of the Diadochi. For the point, name this undefeated conqueror who succeeded Philip II as king of Macedon.", "answer": "<b><u>Alexander the Great</u></b> [or <b><u>Alexander III</u></b> of Macedon; prompt on \u201c<b><u>Alexander</u></b>\u201d]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "While a general, this man was depicted planting his country\u2019s flag at the point d\u2019Arcole. This leader was depicted touching a sick man in Antoine-Jean Gros\u2019 depiction of him <em>Visiting the</em> <em>Plague Victims at Jaffa</em>. Arthur George, the 3rd Earl of Onslaw, commissioned Paul Delaroche to paint a more realistic version of this man <em>Crossing the Alps.</em> For the point, name this diminutive French emperor whose \u201cCoronation\u201d was depicted by Jacques-Louis David.", "answer": "<b><u>Napoleon</u></b> Bonaparte [Napoleon <b><u>Bonaparte</u></b>; or <b><u>Napoleon</u></b> I]  <b>Extra (ONLY READ IF YOU BOTCH A QUESTION!) </b> Leon Gambetta escaped a siege of this city in a hot air balloon. Its streets were widened in a massive 19th century renovation under the direction of Baron Haussman. Charles Garnier won a contest to design its opera house. In 1830 its streets were barricaded during the July Revolution, and in 1870 it was stormed by anarchists and socialists and turned into a commune for a period of two months. For the point, name this capital city of Louis Philip and Napoleon III.  ANSWER: <b><u>Paris</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}